Guide to the C. L. R. James papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series VI: Subject Files, 1952-1992
  - Subseries VI.3: General, 1957-1986
    - Trinidad and Tobago--Documents, 1965, 1972, 1977 (Box 25, Folder 34)
    - Unemployment--United States Senate Study, circa 1959 (Box 25, Folder 35)
    - Union of Revolutionary Organisations (URO), circa 1970s (Box 25, Folder 36)
    - Zimbabwe, 1977-1979 (Box 25, Folder 37)
- Series VII: Photographs and Audio / Visual Material, 1940s-2001
  This series contains photographs, and audio and video tapes.
  - Subseries VII.1: Photographs, circa 1940s-2001
    Most of these photographs are of James, although a few of the photographs are of others. The photographs of James include snapshots from late in his life, more formal portraits and a few photographs from his days in the United States.
    - James, 1949-1980s, Undated ( 2 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 1 to 2)
    - James--Snapshots, circa 1970s-2001 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Cricket, 1960s, Undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Negatives and Contact Sheets, Undated (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Others, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - James's Funeral, (3 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 7 to 9)
    - Slides (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Portraits of James--circa 1970s-1980s (Box 27)
  - Subseries VII.2: Audio / Video Cassette Tapes, circa 1970s-circa 2001
    Audio tapes of interviews and radio broadcasts; and videos of conferences and television programs are held here. The tapes, which are in British and American formats, are of James, and of conferences and programs related to James.
    - Audio Tapes
      - 2819-- American Vision: The time is out of joint (audiotape) James, C.L.R., 1953 April 29 (2 tapes) (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2820--American Vision: The world is my province (audiotape) James, C.L.R., 1953 April 22 (3 tapes) (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2822-2824 2828-- C.L.R. James, from Keith (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2827-- Old World and the New (1953 version) James, C.L.R. 1953 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2830-- On Paul Robeson Speech James,CLR. 1971 (2 tapes) (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2832-- Best of C.L.R. James: America, Cricket, 1983 July (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2838--Best of C.L.R. James: Caribbean, Poland, 1983 July 25 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2835-- Robeson, Paul, Iinterview with CL.R. James, 1983 November 23 (2 tapes) (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2836-- My Childhood -- James, C.L.R., 1983 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2838-- On Marxism to Homeless Students-- James, CL.R., 1987 January (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2840-- James's Death: WBAI Memorial Tribute (audiotape, including audio of James), 5 June 1989 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - 2840-- James's Death: WBAI Memorial Tribute (audiotape, including audio of James), 5 June 1989 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 2842-- Talking History: James and Thompson, 1981 November (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 2843--Three Black Women Writers (C.L.R. James at Black Ink), 1981 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3356--James's Legacy: Bobbie Hill and Me on Nello (audiotape of conversation) Murray, Jim 1985 November 15 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3360-3361--C.L.R. James on Paul Robeson, IAFE, Autobiography 1932-38, 1984 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3363--C.L.R. James on Thackeray and Shakespeare, Interview, 1984 January 28 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3364-- C.L.R. James on the IASB and IAFE, interview, 1984 January 28 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3365-- C.L.R. James, interviewed for Cricket Society, 1984 May 9 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3366--C.L.R. James and Darcus Howe on the Grenada Revolution, 1984 March (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3367--Ross, Ranjitsinhji, Review, 1984 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3368-- C.L. R. James, Interviewed for Photographer's Gallery, 1984 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3369--C.L.R. James Interviewed for South Magazine, 1984 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3370--C.L.R. James on Cricket and I, World Revolution, Toussaint (the play), Interview, 1984 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3371-- C.L.R James, Interviewed for Australian TV and Radio, 1983 September 29 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3372--Hackney Black Alliance, Speech to, 1983 October 29 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3373--Walter Rodney and the Question of Power, 1981 October 23 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3374--C.L.R. James: An Autobiography, continued, 1981 October 23 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3375--C.L.R. James Interviewed for Sunday Telegraph, 1984 February (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - 3375--C.L.R. James Interviewed for Sunday Telegraph, 1984 February (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3376-- C.L.R. James on Women, Interviewed by Anna Grimshaw, 1984 February (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3377-- C.L.R. James on his Autobiography, Interview, 1983 November 22 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3378-- C.L R. James Interviewed for (Dublin) Tribune, 1984 January 12 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3380-- C.L.R. James Interviewed on Cricket for Dublin Sunday Tribune, 1984 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3381-- James's death: C.L.R.'s Funeral, 1989 June (3 tapes) (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3382-- C.L.R. James: His Impact on the Caribbean, panel at C.LR. James: His Intellectual Legacies Conference, Thurton, Rodrick, et al., 1991 April 18 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3383-- C.L.R. James: Personal Memories-- Panel at CL.R James: His Intellectual Legacies Conference-- Grimshaw, Anna, 1991 April 20 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3384-- Thompson, Edward P., Interviewed on WBAI radio, 1977 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3386-- C.L.R. James in the 1980s An Interview with Anna Grimshaw, 1991 April 24 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3387-- C.L.R. James and the Twentieth Century, Brecht Forum Lecture --Murray, Jim, 1989 May 16 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3415-- Coombs, Donna, on Caribbean politics, Smith College Public Lecture, 1988 April 21 (2 tapes) (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3416-- Federici, Silvia, on Marxism and Feminism-- Lecture, 1988 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 3417-- Thurton, Rodrick, on CL.R. James and the Caribbean, 1988 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 4206-- Atlantic World of C.L.R. James (Cambridge Lecture) Hart, Keith, 1996 October 15 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - 4901-- Role of the Black Scholar-- James, C.L.R., 1971 June 18 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 4902-- Black Jacobins and Black Reconstruction-- James, C.L.R., 1971 June 15 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 4903-- Nkrumah, Padmore, and the Ghanaian Revolution-- James, C.L.R., 1971 June 17 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 4904-- On Oliver Cox's Caste, Race, and Class- James, C.L.R., 1971 June 16 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5085--Lamb, Anne, Interview with (on the 1930s), 1986 March 10 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5087-- James, C.L.R., Interviewed by Selwyn Cudjoe, 1983 October 17 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5088-- James, C.L.R. Interviewed by Angus Calder, 1984 March 2 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5090-- C.L. R. James, Remembered by Harry Wicks, 1985 April 30 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5091-- C.LR. Jamcs, Remembered by Betty Hamilton, 1985 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5092-- C.L.R. James, Remembered by John Archer, 1984 November 16 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5093-- C.L.R. James, Remembered by F.A. Ridley, 1986 August 13 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5094-- C.L.R. James, Remembered by Richie Berman, 1987 March 24 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5095-- C.L.R. James, Interviewed by David Scott, 1988 February 4 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5096-- C.L.R. James, Remembered by Constance Webb, 1990 December 9 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5098-- C.L.R. James, Remembered by Charles Van Gelderen, 1984 December 4 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5099-- C.L.R. James, Remembered by Rita Dewar1985 October 18 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5100-- C.L.R. James, Interviewed by Roberto Hodgson, 1986 July 2 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5101-- C.L.R. James, Remembered by Gladys Whittaker, 1985? (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5106-- C.L.R. James, Remembered by Wilson Harris, 1991 June 12 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - 5102--Handsworth Riots of 1985 an Interview with Howard Reid, 1985 November 1 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - 5103-- C.L.R. James, Remembered by Harry Wicks, 1987 August 14 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - 5104-- C.L.R. James, Interviewed for Open Mind, (a Mental Health Journal) James, CL.R., 1987 January 9 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - 5105-- Autobiography: Coming to England-- James Interviewed by Anna Grimshaw, 1984 June 1 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - 5106-- C.L.R. James, Remembered by Wilson Harris, 1991 June 12 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - 5107-- Richard Wright and Me, Lecture at Yale-- Baldwin, James, 1983 November 2 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - 5109-- Paul Robeson: Audio Documentary, Pacifica Radio, 1990s (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - 5112--C.L.R. James on Women and Men in the Caribbean, Interview, 1987 February 24 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - 5132-- C L R. James Interview (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - C.L.R. James Interviewed for Caribbean Focus, 1986 (2 tapes) (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - Constance Webb (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - C.L.R. James at UCLA (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - C.L.R. James: Al Richardson and Anna Grimshaw, 1986 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - C.L.R. James interviewed by John Lewis, Al Richardson, and Anna Grimshaw, 1987 January 26 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - C.L.R. James Memorial-- Southend, 1989 June 24 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - C.L.R. James on the West Indian Writer (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - C.L.R. James Interviewed by Caribbean Politics: Today and Tomorrow (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - CDs
      - Terisa Turner Interview with C.L.R. James (4 discs) (Box 29)
      - Selma James Speaking on Black Jacobins, 2008 (Box 29)
      - Toussaint L'Overture Script (Box 29)
      - C.L.R. James at University of Hull, 1983 (Box 29)
      - The Black Jacobins: A Biography of C.L.R. James Audio Book (Box 29)
      - C.L.R. James: Marx, Cricket, and World Revolution, 2001 (3 discs) (Box 29)
      - C.L.R. James and David Levy, McGill University, 1968 October 13 (Box 29)
      - Unlabeled CDs (2 discs) (Box 29)
      - BBC Radio 4 Arena Recordings (3 CDs) (Box 29)
    - VHS Tapes
      - C.L.R. James-- Talking History with E.P. Thompson (Box 29)
      - Freedom on My Mind (Box 29)
      - Talking History (1 VHS and 1 U-Matic tape) (Box 29)
      - C.L.R. James Lectures on Channel 4 (2 tapes) (Box 29)
      - Paul Robeson-- Here I Stand (Box 29)
      - C.L.R. James Intervewed by Selwyn Cudjoe (Box 29)
- Series VIII: Books From James's Library
  - Books and Periodicals from James's Library (Box 30 to 44)